Finding Aid for McCreery-Fenton family papers, 1842-1935 [microform]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
McCreery-Fenton family papers 1842-1935, 1860-1865
McCreery family
2 microfilms
2011006 mf497c; mf498c
Microfilm of a selection of the papers of the McCreery-Fenton families of Genesee County, Michigan. Civil War correspondence and other papers of William M. Fenton of Fenton and Flint, Michigan, Democratic state senator, and lieutenant governor, later colonel with the 8th Michigan Infantry; correspondence, diaries, and other materials of William B. McCreery of Flint, Michigan, Colonel in the 21st Michigan Infantry during the Civil War; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Fenton McCreery Davison (donor no. 5868 ) and came to the library in 1976.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The original materials of the McCreery-Fenton family papers are held by the Bentley Historical Library.
The McCreery and Fenton families were prominent Genesee county residents some of whose members distinguished themselves in local and state government, as soldiers during the Civil War, and in the United States diplomatic service.
William M. Fenton (1808-1871), for whom the city of Fenton, Michigan was named, was a lawyer, state senator (1846), lieutenant governor (1848, re-elected 1850), mayor of Flint (1858), and Democratic candidate for governor (1864). During the Civil War, although in his fifties, Fenton raised some of the first troops in the state. His initial appointment was as major in the 7th Michigan Infantry. He later transferred to command of the 8th Michigan Infantry. In 1863, he was discharged with the rank of colonel.
His son-in-law, William B. McCreery (1836-1896), also served in the Civil War. As colonel in the 21st Michigan Infantry, McCreery was wounded and captured at the Battle of Chickamauga (1863) and imprisoned for a time at Libby Prison, but escape with others through the famous tunnel. After the war, he became involved in public service. He was mayor of Flint (1865) and state treasurer (1875-1879). He later was selected to be United States Consul to Chile. During his period of service (1890-1891), relations with Chile were difficult as the country underwent a revolution against the Balmaceda administration. There was an attack on U.S. sailors, sometime referred to as the "Baltimore Affair" that threatened to bring the United States into a war with Chile. Assisting McCreery in Chile was his son Fenton R. McCreery (1866-1940) whose subsequent diplomatic career would take him to different countries of Central and South America.
This microfilm edition of a portion of the McCreery-Fenton family collection includes only materials relating to the Civil War service of William M. Fenton and William B. McCreery.
Subjects:
Chickamauga, Battle of, Ga., 1863.; Fredericksburg (Va.), Battle of, 1862.; Libby Prison.; McCreery family.; Thomas, George Henry, 1816-1870.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 7th (1861-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 8th (1861-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 21st (1862-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Fenton family.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Chattanooga (Tenn.), Battle of, 1863.; Fenton, William M., 1808-1871.; Lookout Mountain (Tenn.), Battle of, 1863.; McCreery, William B. (William Barker), 1836-1896.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Women.
Contributors:
Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.; Crapo, Henry Howland, 1804-1869.; Fenton, William M., 1808-1871.; McCreery, William B. (William Barker), 1836-1896.; Robertson, Jno. (John), 1814-1887.; Thomas, George Henry, 1816-1870.; Willcox, Orlando B.
Genre Terms:
Cabinet card photographs.; Photographs.; Stereographs.; Tintypes.
- William M. Fenton
  The William M. Fenton series consists primarily of documentation of his Civil War career. Of interest in addition to correspondence and official documents is a record book from the 8th Michigan Infantry that he maintained. The volume is dated 1861-1862. Fenton also collected other 8th Michigan Infantry related papers such as the diary of Captain Horatio Belcher pertaining to the Fredericksburg campaign. Correspondents include Austin Blair.
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Reel 1)
    - 1842-1843 1853-1859 (Reel 1)
    - 1860 (Reel 1)
    - 1861-1871 (Reel 1)
  - 7th Michigan Infantry papers 1861 (Reel 1)
  - 8th Michigan Infantry papers 1861 (Reel 1)
  - 8th Michigan Infantry record book 1861-1862 (Reel 1)
  - Ninth Army Corps papers (Reel 1)
  - 8th Michigan Infantry discharge papers 1863 (Reel 1)
  - 8th Michigan Infantry miscellaneous, 2 folders (Reel 1)
  - Newsclippings (Reel 1)
  - Diary (7 p.)of a campaign in Virginia (Fredericksburg) by Captain Horatio Belcher, 8th Michigan 1862 (Reel 1)
  - Address by Charles McCreery at 1st reunion of the 8th Michigan Infantry 1867 (Reel 1)
  - Reunion miscellanea, including reminiscences presented posthumously 1903 (Reel 1)
  - Miscellanea (Reel 1)
  - Newsclippings, 2 folders (Reel 1)
  - Masonic funeral service 1871 (Reel 1)
- William B. McCreery
  The William B. McCreery series consists of correspondence, Civil War documents, and miscellaneous largely to his war service. Some of McCreery's correspondents include Austin Blair, Henry H. Crapo, John Robertson, William S. Rosencrans, and Orland B. Wilcox.
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Reel 2)
    - 1861-June 1864 (Reel 2)
    - July 1864-1866 (Reel 2)
  - Other papers
    - Certificates of Civil War service 1862-1864 (Reel 2)
    - Papers concerning his presumed death at the Battle of Chickamauga and later discharge from the army 1863-1864 (Reel 2)
    - Miscellanea concerning operations of the 21st Michigan Infantry 1863-1864, 2 folders (Reel 2)
    - Papers concerning reunions of the 21st Michigan Infantry 1889-1929 (Reel 2)
    - Speech concerning escape from Libby Prison 1889 (published in 1893), including newspaper clippings about the escape (Reel 2)
    - Scrapbook concerning 21st Michigan Infantry and the escape of McCreery and others from Libby Prison (Reel 2)
    - Speech concerning General George H. Thomas, Commander of the Army of the Cumberland 1895 (Reel 2)
    - Papers concerning mining interest 1895 (Reel 2)
    - Newspaper clippings (Reel 2)
    - Miscellanea (Reel 2)
    - Papers concerning the death of William B. McCreery (Reel 2)
    - Civil War miscellanea, 2 folders (Reel 2)
- Visual Materials
  The Photograph series includes commercially produced photographs and stereographs from the period of the Civil War.
  - Tintypes
    - Three Civil War soldiers (Reel 2)
    - Soldiers before tent (Reel 2)
    - Adelaide B. Fenton, 3 copies (Reel 2)
  - Cartes de visite
    - Three portraits (two of women) with stamps 1862-1864 (Reel 2)
  - Photographs
    - Civil War era photos (Reel 2)